A Guide to Materials on Women
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- Woman's Christian Temperance Union of Virginia Programs 1903-1941, 24 items.
  Programs from annual state conventions. #1763
- Woman's Christian Temperance Union (W.C.T.U.) of Virginia 1882-1958, 365 items.
  W.C.T.U. was a woman's organization whose purpose was to prevent the sale and consumption of alcohol in Virginia. The collection contains correspondence, convention programs and proceedings, publications, photographs, scrapbook, minutes and printed material. #1750, 2119-e-f.
- Works Project Administration (W.P.A.) Folklore Collection 1934-1943, 34 boxes
  The papers of the Virginia Writers' Project of the Works Project Administration concerning Virginia folklore. Papers include hundreds of life histories, reports, radio scripts, ethnic reports, ex-slave accounts, folksongs, and ghost stories. #1547
- Willard Huntington Wright 1899-1978, 1563 items.
  W. H. Wright wrote under the pen name, S. S. Van Dine, and created the detective character, Philo Vance. Most of the collection consists of correspondence between Wright, and his wife, Katherine Boynton Wright, and their daughter Beverley. Due to his work and their fragile health, mental and physical, the Wrights spent most of their 23-year marriage apart. They eventually divorced in 1930. These letters reflect a troubled marriage and a dysfunctional family. Toward the end of their marriage and Wright's life, letters between him and Katherine primarily concerned money disputes and the life of their wayward daughter, Beverley, who led a bohemian lifestyle. Correspondence, 1928, strongly indicates Beverley had lesbian tendencies which upset her mother, but not her father. #9701-a
- Young-Munford-Ellis Family Papers 1789-1940, 350 items.
  papers of the Ellis and Munford families of Richmond, Virginia, and of the Young family of Fredericksburg, Virginia. There are documents relating to Rosetta Hunter, a slave, who was bought by Charles Ellis in February, 1839. She commanded the price of $850 and was held in high esteem by the family and eventually became the beloved "Mammy." Documents include her bill of sale and matters relating to her estate as well as her obituary. There is a document, January 27, 1840, releasing fourteen year old Lucy Ann Hunter, a "bright mulatto" from slavery. Other items of interest are Margaret Ellis' letters to her son Powhatan Ellis during the Civil War, a touching letter from Charles Ellis to his sister Jane Eubank (August 16, 1851) congratulating her on her recent marriage, a letter from Sallie Munford to her Uncle Powhie describing her activities as young woman (January 12, 1860), and the letters from Charles Ellis Munford while a student at the University of Virginia to his sister Sallie Munford (1860) are particularly enjoyable. Unfortunately, Charles was killed in 1862 during the Battle of Malvern Hill. #2516